Finding Aid for Joseph H. Bunzel papers, 1936-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Joseph H. Bunzel papers 1936-1975
Bunzel, Joseph Hans, 1907-
1 linear foot
861001 Aa 2
Sociologist and researcher into the subject of gerontology, particularly gerontophobia. Speeches, reprints, manuscripts of writings; also research materials, including reports and collected data, and correspondence, relating in part to his work on the Research Committee of the New York City Mayor's Advisory Committee for the Aged, 1949-1951.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was given to the Institute of Gerontology of the University of Michigan by Mrs. Bunzel (accession no. 78-003) and then transferred to the Michigan Historical Collections in 1984. (donor no. 6160 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Joseph Hans Bunzel was born in Graz, Austria, September 20, 1907. He received a J.D. in Social Science from the University of Vienna in 1932 and a Diplomate in Business Administration in 1933. he also attended medical school in Vienna and studied in a number of other universities: University of Dijon, psychology, 1932; Sorbonne, sociology, 1932; Johns Hopkins University, sociology and history of medicine, 1940-1942; University of Pittsburgh, psychology, tests and measurements, 1949-1950. In 1938 he married Gertrude Godwyn Bunzel and left Austria; in 1945 he became a United States citizen.
Bunzel's career included research, teaching, and clinical positions. His work in sociology spanned his entire career. He was Coordinator and Director of the Curriculum Study, Colleges of Western North Carolina (1941-1942); in housing and health in the Baltimore City Health Department (1942-1943), Pittsburgh Housing Association and Allegheny Board of Assistance (1943-1946 and 1950-1957), National Association of Housing Officials and Chicago Real Estate Corporation (1948-1949) and the New York City Board of Guardians (1951). It was as Director of Research for the New York City Mayor's Advisory Committee for the Aged that Bunzel began to focus his research interest on aging. During his tenure with this committee research was conducted on several projects simultaneously. From 1956-1967 Bunzel was a professor of social science at the College of William and Mary, Virginia Union University, the University of North Dakota, and St. John's University in Minnesota. In 1965 he worked on a research planning project in the geriatric ward of Fergus Falls State Hospital in Minnesota. From 1967 until his death, Bunzel was professor of sociology at the State University of New York College at Buffalo.
Throughout his years of teaching, Bunzel produced numerous papers on gerontology, particularly on the concept of gerontophobia. He was the main author of the report of the New York City Mayor's Committee for the Aged. He authored a column in Strait, the student newspaper of the State University of New York College at Buffalo, dealing primarily with gerontological concerns. In addition, he continued his research and publishing in sociology, doing much writing on Ludwig Gumplowicz.
The papers deal primarily with Bunzel's work and writings from 1936 to 1975, especially with the concept of gerontophobia. The papers also contain some items relating to Bunzel's work in other areas of sociology. The collection has been divided into two series: Papers and Research.
Subjects:
Older people.; Aging.; Gerontology.; New York (N.Y.). Mayor's Advisory Committee for the Aged.
- Papers
  The first series, papers, consists of papers, speeches and reprints authored by Bunzel from 1936 to 1975. Included are "Concept, Meaning and Treatment of Gerontophobia," issues of Strait and copies of Bunzel's column in Strait. Papers from a number of conferences are included, as are course materials. This series includes Bunzel's unpublished manuscript "Gumplowicz as a legal and political figure."
  - Writings, 1936-1973 and undated, 13 folders (Box 1)
  - Existentialism series, ca. 1956-1964 (Box 1)
  - "Gumplowicz as a legal and political figure," 1970 (Box 1)
  - "Notes on Slavery," 1974 (Box 1)
  - "Security under Law," 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Strait
    - Entire issues, 1971-1973, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Bunzel articles, 1971-1975 (Box 1)
    - Papers by other authors, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Research
  The second series, Research, includes reports, data and some correspondence from a number of Bunzel's projects. The largest portion of this series comprises material from the Research Committee of the New York City Mayor's Advisory Committee for the Aged. This committee conducted numerous research projects during the years 1949-1951. The series includes some data, reports on separate projects as well as on the work of the entire committee, correspondence and minutes of the committee and interim and final reports of the research.
  - Self Study of Junior Colleges of Western North Carolina, 1941 (Box 1)
  - New York City Mayor's Advisory Committee for the Aged, 1949-1953
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Minutes (Box 1)
    - Notes (Box 1)
    - Project questionnaires (Box 1)
    - Proposal to Rockefeller Foundation (Box 1)
    - Report, 1953 "NYC Senior Citizens-Our Most Neglected Resource"
      - Interim reports, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Drafts (Box 1)
      - Papers, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Volume 1 (Box 1)
      - Volume 2 (Box 1)
      - Volume 3 (Box 1)
      - Volume 2, equivalent (Box 1)
  - Fergus Falls State Hospital Research Project, 1965 (Box 1)
  - St. Cloud Study of Gerontophobia, 1966 (Box 1)
Related Material
The Ne York State University at Buffalo also has a Joseph Bunzel collection.